[
  {
    "id": 1,
    "question": "Each of the following mature cells has a nucleus EXCEPT",
    "options": ["lymphocyte", "monocyte", "erythrocyte", "basophil"],
    "answer": ["erythrocyte"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 2,
    "question": "Which sequence is correct for the following events:\n 1.fibrinogen→ fibrin\n 2. Clot retraction\n 3.Formation of thromboplastin\n 4. Prothrombin → thrombin",
    "options": ["3,4, 1,2", "1,2,3,4", "4,3,1,2", "3,2,1,4"],
    "answer": ["3,4, 1,2"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 3,
    "question": "Which of the following is not a physical characteristic of blood?",
    "options": [
      "PH range of 7.35 to 7.45",
      "temperature of 38◦c",
      "average volume of 5-6 litres in a male",
      "8% of body weight"
    ],
    "answer": ["PH range of 7.35 to 7.45"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 4,
    "question": "Which of the following statements about factors involved in the formation of blood cells is false?",
    "options": [
      "cytokines called colony stimulating factors and interleukins regulate the formation and activities of phagocytes and leukocytes involved in nonspecific defense and immunity",
      "thrombopoietin produced in the kidney regulates the clotting activities of platelets",
      "erythropoietin and thrombopoietin may be referred to as both hormones and homopoietic growth factors",
      "all of the above",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["none of the above"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 5,
    "question": "Sites of hemopoiesis in the adult include all of the following except",
    "options": [
      "liver",
      "sternum",
      "cranial bones",
      "head of femur",
      "all marrows"
    ],
    "answer": ["all marrows"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 6,
    "question": "1. The heme portion of hemoglobin contains iron that binds reversibly with oxygen. In addition to oxygen and carbon dioxide transport;\n2. hemoglobin functions in blood pressure regulation by ferrying nitricoxide throughout the body",
    "options": [
      "both statements are true",
      "both statements are false",
      "the first statement is true, the second is false",
      "the second statement is true; the first is false",
      "all of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["both statements are true"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 7,
    "question": "Fred’s blood was determined to be AB positive. What does this mean?",
    "options": [
      "antibodies to A and B are present in the erythrocytes",
      "there are no antibodies to A, to B , or to Rh antigens in the plasma",
      "his blood lacks Rh factor",
      "all of the above",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "there are no antibodies to A, to B , or to Rh antigens in the plasma"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 8,
    "question": "Which of the following lead(s) to an increase in the rate of RBC production?",
    "options": [
      "hypoxia",
      "testosterone",
      "erythropoietin",
      "all of these",
      "none of these"
    ],
    "answer": ["all of these"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 9,
    "question": "A, B and Rh(D) are examples of ________ found in RBC membranes",
    "options": [
      "antibodies",
      "agglutinogens",
      "isoantigens",
      "both agglutinogens and isoantigens"
    ],
    "answer": ["both agglutinogens and isoantigens"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 10,
    "question": "Monocytes migrate into the body tissues to become phagocytic cells called",
    "options": [
      "macrophages",
      "fibroblasts",
      "lymphocytes",
      "polymorphs",
      "monoblasts"
    ],
    "answer": ["macrophages"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 11,
    "question": "Neutrophils provide weapons against bacteria in the form of",
    "options": ["lysozymes", "defensins", "oxidants", "all of these", "weapon"],
    "answer": ["all of these"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 12,
    "question": "The white blood cells that typically increase in response to allergic conditions or parasitic infections are",
    "options": [
      "neutrophils",
      "eosinophils",
      "basophils",
      "monocytes",
      "lymphocytes"
    ],
    "answer": ["eosinophils"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 13,
    "question": "Platelets",
    "options": [
      "have a longer lifespan than RBC",
      "develop from worn out RBC",
      "are more numerous than RBC",
      "promote blood clotting and blood vessel repair"
    ],
    "answer": ["promote blood clotting and blood vessel repair"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 14,
    "question": "Concerning plasma",
    "options": [
      "is an ICF",
      "it is an ECF",
      "it is found in both ICF and ECF",
      "the differences between plasma and ICF is their protein concentration",
      "its protein concentration is about 5 times that of ICF"
    ],
    "answer": ["it is an ECF"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 15,
    "question": "Normal human red cells",
    "options": [
      "are released into circulation as immature cells called reticulocytes",
      "live for about 10 days",
      "rely on mitochondria for their ATP production",
      "they are rod shaped"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "are released into circulation as immature cells called reticulocytes"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 16,
    "question": "Regarding the platelets:",
    "options": [
      "are present in greater number than red cells",
      "secrete the main clotting factors",
      "will adhere to the walls of damaged blood vessels",
      "is the last cellular response for bleeding",
      "will adhere to the walls of damaged blood vessels"
    ],
    "answer": ["are present in greater number than red cells"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 17,
    "question": "Regarding inflammatory response",
    "options": [
      "tissue swelling is the fist stage of inflammatory response",
      "mast cells secrete chemotactic agents that attract lymphocytes",
      "macrophages secrete vasoactive materials during inflammatory response",
      "the inflammatory response can be triggered by antibody binding to the surface of microorganism"
    ],
    "answer": ["tissue swelling is the fist stage of inflammatory response"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 18,
    "question": "Regarding the natural immune system",
    "options": [
      "neutrophils only destroy bacteria circulating in the blood",
      "macrophages use nitrous oxide to kill bacteria they have engulfed",
      "complement kills bacteria prior to their uptake by phagocytes",
      "the monocytes of the blood are the precursors of tissue macrophages",
      "the monocytes of the blood are the precursors of immunity"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "the monocytes of the blood are the precursors of tissue macrophages"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 19,
    "question": "Regarding the lymphocytes",
    "options": [
      "the lymphocytes are the most abundant white cells of the blood",
      "lymphocytes only leave the blood at sites of inflammation",
      "B lymphocytes respond to antigens in the extracellular fluid",
      "all T lymphocytes become plasma cells after they have been stimulated"
    ],
    "answer": ["B lymphocytes respond to antigens in the extracellular fluid"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 20,
    "question": "Regarding the functions of T lymphocytes:",
    "options": [
      "T lymphocytes mature in the thyroid gland",
      "all T cells secrete cytotoxic materials",
      "they function like B- lymphocytes",
      "T- cells respond to proteins on the surface of host cells"
    ],
    "answer": ["T- cells respond to proteins on the surface of host cells"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 21,
    "question": "About antibodies",
    "options": [
      "The antigen receptor on a lymphocyte has the same specificity as the antibody it secretes",
      "IgM cross the placenta and provides a fetus with antibody protection",
      "T lymphocyte secrete IgM in response to a first infection",
      "antibody molecules have two identical antigen binding sites in the Fe region",
      "they are activated by monocytes"
    ],
    "answer": ["they are activated by monocytes"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 22,
    "question": "Decreased number of megakaryocytes results in",
    "options": [
      "increased rate of infection",
      "defective clot formation",
      "decreased antibody production",
      "none of these"
    ],
    "answer": ["defective clot formation"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 23,
    "question": "Measuring total body water requires",
    "options": [
      "Evans blue dye",
      "Tritium marked water",
      "leishman dye",
      "Romanowsky group of dyes",
      "chromium labeled EDTA"
    ],
    "answer": ["Tritium marked water"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 24,
    "question": "In the ABO blood group system transfused cells are likely to be affected by an antigen-antibody reaction when",
    "options": [
      "group A blood is transfused to a group B person",
      "group O blood is transfused to a group AB person",
      "group O blood is transfused to a group A person",
      "group A blood is transfused to a group AB person",
      "group B blood is transfused to a group AB person"
    ],
    "answer": ["group A blood is transfused to a group B person"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 25,
    "question": "The conversion of fibrinogen to fibrin",
    "options": [
      "is promoted by prothrombin , a proteolytic enzyme",
      "involves the disruption of certain peptide linkages in fibrinogen",
      "is not inhibited by heparin, a strong electronegative substance",
      "all of the above",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "involves the disruption of certain peptide linkages in fibrinogen"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 26,
    "question": "Thirst is",
    "options": [
      "produced by a fall in plasma tonicity when though blood volume is normal",
      "produced by rise in blood volume even though blood tonicity is normal",
      "relieved when water is drunk before the water has been absorbed and the blood volume and tonicity returned to normal",
      "produced by stimulation of certain areas in the thalamus",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["none of the above"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 27,
    "question": "Erythropoiesis",
    "options": [
      "is stimulated when a person descends to a height where the atmospheric pressure is doubled",
      "occurs only in the bone marrow",
      "is dependent on normal gastric secretory activity",
      "is stimulated by a rise in the pressure of carbondioxide (PCO₂) in the arterial blood",
      "is less in high altitude"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "is stimulated by a rise in the pressure of carbondioxide (PCO₂) in the arterial blood"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 28,
    "question": "The granulocytes in the blood of normal people",
    "options": [
      "multinucleated",
      "are incapable of crossing capillary walls",
      "are derived from the bone marrow",
      "are confined within blood",
      "flow in the main axial stem of blood"
    ],
    "answer": ["are derived from the bone marrow"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 29,
    "question": "Lymphocytes",
    "options": [
      "in the africans from 1-2 % of the white cell count",
      "cannot be transformed by a suitable stimulus into plasma cells",
      "cannot cross the capillary wall",
      "are motile",
      "none of the above is correct"
    ],
    "answer": ["are motile"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 30,
    "question": "Antibodies",
    "options": [
      "are formed in response to exposure to antigen in early fetal life",
      "tend to be produced in smaller quantities in response to the second than in response to the first exposure to antigen",
      "which circulate as free immunoglobulins are produced by the B-lymphocytes",
      "are all lipids",
      "all of the above is correct"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "which circulate as free immunoglobulins are produced by the B-lymphocytes"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 31,
    "question": "Bleeding from a small cut in the skin",
    "options": [
      "is normally diminished in normal people",
      "ceases within 5 minutes in normal people",
      "would prolong if factor VIII is absent",
      "is likely to be greater if the skin is cold than if it is warm",
      "none of the above is correct"
    ],
    "answer": ["would prolong if factor VIII is absent"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 32,
    "question": "Bilirubin",
    "options": [
      "is a vigroid pigment",
      "tissues from red cell breakdown sites to the liver dissolved in plasma in an unbound form",
      "contains iron",
      "is necessary for digestion and absorption of fat in the intestine",
      "is a porphyrin pigment derived from haem"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "is necessary for digestion and absorption of fat in the intestine"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 33,
    "question": "Monocytes",
    "options": [
      "originate from precursor cells in the lymph nodes",
      "are proteolytic",
      "may migrate from blood into tissues",
      "can manufacture certain immunoglobulins",
      "all of the above are correct"
    ],
    "answer": ["may migrate from blood into tissues"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 34,
    "question": "Erythrocytes",
    "options": [
      "measure about 1-2 microns",
      "contains carbonic hydrase",
      "swell up and burst when placed in hypertonic solution",
      "generate energy from glucose so that oxygen may combine with haemoglobin"
    ],
    "answer": ["measure about 1-2 microns"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 35,
    "question": "Thrombocytes are important in stopping bleeding that",
    "options": [
      "they can release thrombin , which have a role to play in clotting process",
      "the bleeding time tend to increase when the platelet count is high",
      "when exposed to collagen they become active and loose",
      "a fall in plateletcount prolongs the clotting time before the bleeding time is affected",
      "they get digested very quickly"
    ],
    "answer": ["when exposed to collagen they become active and loose"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 36,
    "question": "Human plasma albumin:",
    "options": [
      "makes a greater contribution to the colloid osmotic pressure of the plasma than does globulin",
      "is freely filtered at renal glomerulus",
      "is involved in the carriage of oxygen in the blood",
      "is not involved in the carriage of carbondioxide",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "makes a greater contribution to the colloid osmotic pressure of the plasma than does globulin"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 37,
    "question": "If a person has group B blood",
    "options": [
      "He may have the genotype AB",
      "His father might have group O blood",
      "his father can only have either group B blood",
      "and his wife also has blood group B, all their children will have group B",
      "He will have antibody B in his plasma"
    ],
    "answer": ["His father might have group O blood"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 38,
    "question": "Total body water",
    "options": [
      "forms a smaller percentage of body weight in fat persons than in thin",
      "compress half to two-thirds of body water in young adults",
      "is smaller proportion of body weight in men than in women",
      "it is about 42mls"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "forms a smaller percentage of body weight in fat persons than in thin"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 39,
    "question": "Extracellular body fluid is different from intracellular body fluid in man in that",
    "options": [
      "it has smaller volume",
      "it has lower tonicity",
      "its anions are mainly organic",
      "it has higher potassium-sodium molar rate",
      "its PH is more acidic"
    ],
    "answer": ["it has smaller volume"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 40,
    "question": "Monocytes are leucocytes which",
    "options": [
      "are formed from the lymphoid stem cells",
      "they act as tissue macrophages",
      "proliferate into killer cells",
      "they form antibodies",
      "their diameters range between 10 - 12 microns"
    ],
    "answer": ["they act as tissue macrophages"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 41,
    "question": "Which of the following haematological parameters is incorrect?",
    "options": [
      "mean cell volume range between 76-96",
      "mean cell haemoglobin range between 27- 32 pqHb/ cell",
      "mean cell haemoglobin concentration range between 300-350 / litre of cells",
      "Hb concentration in non-pregnant women range between 14.5 g/100 mls of blood",
      "PCV for women range between 0.34- 0.47"
    ],
    "answer": ["PCV for women range between 0.34- 0.47"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 42,
    "question": "Which of the following substance is not an essential ingredient for erythropoiesis?",
    "options": [
      "carbohydrate",
      "iron",
      "cobalt and copper",
      "thyroxin",
      "pyridoxine"
    ],
    "answer": ["carbohydrate"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 43,
    "question": "All are true of the Rh blood group except",
    "options": [
      "it is associated with haemolytic transfusion reactions",
      "the antigens are highly immunogenic",
      "it is found in rhesus monkey",
      "it is associated with haemolytic disease of the newborn",
      "they are five main antigens C,c, D, E and e"
    ],
    "answer": ["they are five main antigens C,c, D, E and e"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 44,
    "question": "Which of the following is incorrect about Basophils?",
    "options": [
      "they are the least numerous of the WBC",
      "they have dark coarse granules, which stain blue",
      "they contain heparin and histamine",
      "they are the largest WBCs",
      "they have obscured nuclei"
    ],
    "answer": ["they are the largest WBCs"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 45,
    "question": "The % range of body water that is total body water in infants is",
    "options": ["45-60%", "54-70%", "65-75%", "40-60%", "none of the abov"],
    "answer": ["65-75%"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 46,
    "question": "The amount of water in the body does not depend on",
    "options": ["fat content", "weight", "age", "sex", "height"],
    "answer": ["height"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 47,
    "question": "ICF volume can be measured using all but one of the following in the ECF except",
    "options": [
      "ATP",
      "Hexamonophosphate",
      "urea",
      "carnosine",
      "phosphocreatine"
    ],
    "answer": ["urea"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 48,
    "question": "All of the functions below are carried out by blood except",
    "options": [
      "reproductive function",
      "regulatory function",
      "protective function",
      "transportation",
      "excretory function"
    ],
    "answer": ["reproductive function"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 49,
    "question": "The biconcave shape of the RBC is advantageous to it because",
    "options": [
      "it provides a higher surface area to volume ratio",
      "it enables its membrane to have low tension",
      "it makes it to be more flexible",
      "A and C only are correct",
      "A,B,C above are correct"
    ],
    "answer": ["A,B,C above are correct"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 50,
    "question": "Which of these components of blood does not originate from the multipurpose stem cells?",
    "options": [
      "Basophils",
      "platelets",
      "neutrophils",
      "B- lymphocytes",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["none of the above"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 51,
    "question": "All but one of these factors increase the rate of RBC production",
    "options": [
      "erythrocyte stimulating factor",
      "Hypoxia",
      "Thyroxine",
      "Thromboxane",
      "intrinsic factor"
    ],
    "answer": ["Thromboxane"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 52,
    "question": "All of the following is true of the Rhesus blood group except",
    "options": [
      "85% of all Africans have the anti D antigen",
      "in the rhesus blood group there is no preformed antibody",
      "any of the ABO, blood groups can be RH -ve or Rh +ve",
      "Antibody D can only develop when a RH -ve person is exposed to a Rh+e bloo",
      "the rhesus blood group has 3 genotypes"
    ],
    "answer": ["85% of all Africans have the anti D antigen"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 53,
    "question": "The mean value for adult plasma bilirubin concentration is",
    "options": [
      "0.5gm/100mls of blood",
      "0.8gm/100mls of blood",
      "0.5mg/100mls of blood",
      "0.8/100mls of blood",
      "0.2gm/100 of blood"
    ],
    "answer": ["0.5mg/100mls of blood"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 54,
    "question": "RBC will shrink if placed for several hours in a saline solution of",
    "options": ["0.009%", "9%", "0.5%", "0.9%", "none of the above"],
    "answer": ["9%"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 55,
    "question": "One of the following is not true of the haem molecule",
    "options": [
      "it gives blood its characteristic red colour",
      "it has molecular weight of about 65,000",
      "it contains iron",
      "Each of the Hb molecules has four haem",
      "synthesis of Hb starts in the erythroblast"
    ],
    "answer": ["it has molecular weight of about 65,000"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 56,
    "question": "All of these clotting factors when absent in blood will prevent clot formation except",
    "options": [
      "fibrinogen",
      "Anti Haemophilic Globulin",
      "Factor IV",
      "Thromboxane",
      "prothrombin"
    ],
    "answer": ["Anti Haemophilic Globulin"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 57,
    "question": "Bleeding time can be prolonged by",
    "options": [
      "lack of RBCs",
      "polycytemia",
      "lack of fibrin stabilizing factor",
      "neutrophilia",
      "Thrombocytopenia"
    ],
    "answer": ["lack of fibrin stabilizing factor"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 58,
    "question": "The RBC status of an individual can be as of these factors except",
    "options": [
      "RBC count",
      "Haematocrit",
      "Haemoglobin concentration",
      "Anaemia",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["none of the above"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 59,
    "question": "Which of the following statements is true of leucocytes",
    "options": [
      "they are non-nucleated",
      "they are confined to blood",
      "they move in the main axial stream of blood flow",
      "the majority of them are less than 10 microns in diameter",
      "they are chemotaxic"
    ],
    "answer": ["they are chemotaxic"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 60,
    "question": "All are functions of blood except",
    "options": [
      "transportation",
      "thermoregulation",
      "osmoregulation",
      "Haemostasis",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["none of the above"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 61,
    "question": "Total plasma osmolarity is determined by",
    "options": [
      "dissolved ions",
      "water concentration",
      "plasma protein",
      "colloid osmotic pressure",
      "osmolar concentration of K+ and Na+"
    ],
    "answer": ["dissolved ions"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 62,
    "question": "The rhesus blood group status is one of the following except",
    "options": [
      "inherited in the mendelian fashion",
      "may differ for father and child",
      "is defined by antibodies in plasma",
      "is most commonly Rh negative in Africans",
      "can be tested using RBC coagulation reaction"
    ],
    "answer": ["is most commonly Rh negative in Africans"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 63,
    "question": "Circulating white blood cells",
    "options": [
      "measure about 5 microns in diameter",
      "mainly consists of megakaryocytes",
      "can leave the circulation at inflammation sites",
      "are directly derived from lymphoid cells"
    ],
    "answer": ["can leave the circulation at inflammation sites"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 64,
    "question": "Which of the following statements is not true of monocytes",
    "options": [
      "they are the largest blood cells",
      "they are granular",
      "they do not form antibodies",
      "they have nuclei that vary in shape",
      "their diameters range between 16-20 microns"
    ],
    "answer": ["they have nuclei that vary in shape"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 65,
    "question": "In the fibrinolytic system fibrin cannot digest on of the following factors",
    "options": [
      "factor I",
      "factor XIII",
      "factor V",
      "factor VIII",
      "factor IX"
    ],
    "answer": ["factor I"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 66,
    "question": "Which of the statements below is most correct for platelets",
    "options": [
      "measure about 8 microns in diameter",
      "are small pieces of cytoplasm with small nuclei",
      "are very important for homeostasis",
      "are made from megakaryocyte cells in bone marrow",
      "are about 4,000-11,000/mm³ in man"
    ],
    "answer": ["are about 4,000-11,000/mm³ in man"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 67,
    "question": "All but one of the following significantly affects ESR",
    "options": [
      "Fibrinogen",
      "viscosity",
      "rouleaux formation",
      "platelets",
      "plasma proteins"
    ],
    "answer": ["platelets"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 68,
    "question": "Which one is incorrect about blood clotting?",
    "options": [
      "it is promoted by platelet plugging",
      "it is initiated by tissue thromboplastin in the extrinsic pathway",
      "it does not stimulate fibrinolysis",
      "it requires Ca²ᶧ",
      "defects usually prolong bleeding"
    ],
    "answer": ["it does not stimulate fibrinolysis"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 69,
    "question": "Which is not correct of interferon",
    "options": [
      "it is a protein produced in the body in response to bacterial invasion",
      "it inhibits viral replication",
      "it is non-specific",
      "it is important for viral infection",
      "it is not important for bacterial infection"
    ],
    "answer": ["it is not important for bacterial infection"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 70,
    "question": "The T- lymphocytes",
    "options": [
      "have immunoglobulins on the surface of their membranes",
      "proliferate to form a clone of plasma cells",
      "may contain proteins, which allows antigens permeate through them",
      "greatly depend on the cooperation of macrophages in its function",
      "have T- specific surfangce antigens"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "greatly depend on the cooperation of macrophages in its function"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 71,
    "question": "During platelet plug formation all these substances are produced except",
    "options": [
      "Thromboplastin",
      "protacyclin",
      "thromboxane",
      "Adenosine diphosphate",
      "serotonin"
    ],
    "answer": ["protacyclin"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 72,
    "question": "Vit K. is required for the following blood clotting factors except",
    "options": ["III", "II", "VII", "IX", "X"],
    "answer": ["III"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 73,
    "question": "Plasma fibrinogen concentration is ...........gram %",
    "options": [" 3.8", "0.3", "2.3", "3.0", "0.38"],
    "answer": ["0.3"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 74,
    "question": "The cell volume of an RBC is expected to:",
    "options": [
      "To remain the same in hypotonic solution",
      "increase in a hypertonic solution",
      "remain the same in a 100mosmol per litre NaCl Solution",
      "stay constant in a 300mosmol per litre of urea",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["none of the above"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 75,
    "question": "Which is not true of ABO blood group",
    "options": [
      "Group O is universal donor",
      "A group O has no antigen on the surface of RBC",
      "group O individual has no agglutinin in the plasma",
      "group A individual has antigen A on the surface of RBC",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["group O individual has no agglutinin in the plasma"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 76,
    "question": "All these are clotting factors except",
    "options": [
      "prothrombin",
      "iron",
      "calcium",
      "christmas factor",
      "thromboplastin"
    ],
    "answer": ["iron"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 77,
    "question": "During hemoglobin recycling in the spleen , heme is initially converted into",
    "options": [
      "bilirubin",
      "Bilverdin",
      "Urobilin",
      "Urobilinogen",
      "splenectomy"
    ],
    "answer": ["Bilverdin"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 78,
    "question": "Excessive destruction of erythrocytes is characteristic of",
    "options": [
      "Thalassemia",
      "Aplastic anaemia",
      "pernicious anemia",
      "hemolytic anemia",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["hemolytic anemia"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 79,
    "question": "Erythrocytes",
    "options": [
      "enter the circulation only after becoming fully mature",
      "undergo mitosis iin the circulation in response to erythropoietin",
      "are removed from the circulation after about 120 days by macrophages in the spleen, liver and bone marrow",
      "have mitochondria and are capable of oxidative respiration",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "are removed from the circulation after about 120 days by macrophages in the spleen, liver and bone marrow"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 80,
    "question": "Which of the following cell types is specifically responsible for humoral immunity",
    "options": [
      "T cells",
      "B cells",
      "leukocytes",
      "natural killer cell",
      "lymphocytes"
    ],
    "answer": ["B cells"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 81,
    "question": "A substance that can elicit an immune response is called",
    "options": [
      "complement",
      "an interferon",
      "a histamin",
      "an antibody",
      "an antigen"
    ],
    "answer": ["an antigen"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 82,
    "question": "Antibodies are",
    "options": [
      "amino acids",
      "lipids",
      "carbohydrates",
      "proteins",
      "nucleus"
    ],
    "answer": ["proteins"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 83,
    "question": "Which of the following activates platelets during hemostasis",
    "options": [
      "Eosinophil degranulation",
      "exposed collagen or endothelial basement membrane",
      "fibrin thread formation",
      "thromboplastin",
      "factor VII"
    ],
    "answer": ["exposed collagen or endothelial basement membrane"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 84,
    "question": "What kind of cells wander the interstitial fluid ingesting whatever bacteria and infected cell they encounter and recognize",
    "options": [
      "neutrophils",
      "monocytes",
      "lymphocytes",
      "macrophages",
      "interferons"
    ],
    "answer": ["macrophages"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 85,
    "question": "What is the body’s first line of defense against infection ?",
    "options": [
      "several nonspecific antibodies",
      "several nonspecific amino acid toxins",
      "several non specific obstacles such as skin and mucus",
      "several nonspecific antimicrobial chemicals",
      "both c and d"
    ],
    "answer": ["both c and d"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 86,
    "question": "Blood group antigens are",
    "options": [
      "attached o the haemoglobin molecule",
      "inherited characteristics carried by the autosomes",
      "inherited as recessive characteristics",
      "are found only in blood cells",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["inherited characteristics carried by the autosomes"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 87,
    "question": "Eosinophils in the blood:",
    "options": [
      "comprise about a quarter of all the granulocytes",
      "account for most of the increase in white cell count caused by acute infections",
      "are sites of antibody manufacture",
      "have typically bilobbed nuclei",
      "have dark blue granules"
    ],
    "answer": ["have typically bilobbed nuclei"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 88,
    "question": "Erythrocyte sedimentation rate",
    "options": [
      "is the same in women and women",
      "has a value of 18mmm/min",
      "can be affected by fibrin concentration",
      "has several factors one of which is realeaux formation affecting it",
      "is a specific test for inflammatory conditions"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "has several factors one of which is realeaux formation affecting it"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 89,
    "question": "ICF volume can be measured using all but one of the following substances",
    "options": [
      "sucrose",
      "titrated water",
      "thiosulphate",
      "inulin",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["none of the above"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 90,
    "question": "Which of the following measurements cannot be used to assess RBC status ?",
    "options": [
      "RBC count",
      "Haematocrit",
      "haemoglobin concentration",
      "Anaemia",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["Anaemia"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 91,
    "question": "The following conditions can result in excessive bleeding in humans except",
    "options": [
      "thrombocytopenia",
      "vit. K deficiency",
      "Haemophilia",
      "Von Willbrand’s disease",
      "leucocytopenia"
    ],
    "answer": ["Haemophilia"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 92,
    "question": "Iron deficiency anaemia is",
    "options": [
      "more common in men than in women",
      "is characterized by large, pale red blood cells",
      "should be treated with intramuscular injections of iron",
      "is the form of anaemia typically found following chronic blood loss from the body",
      "none of the above is correct"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "is the form of anaemia typically found following chronic blood loss from the body"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 93,
    "question": "Plasma is composed of all of the following except",
    "options": ["globins", "water", "albumin", "inorganic ions", "antibodies"],
    "answer": ["globins"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 94,
    "question": "All but one of these factors promote erythropoeisis",
    "options": [
      "erythropoietin",
      "hypoxia",
      "vitamin B12",
      "thromboplastin",
      "ACTH"
    ],
    "answer": ["thromboplastin"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 95,
    "question": "What is the normal platelet count in an adult man?",
    "options": [
      "5000-11000 platelets/mm²",
      "50,000-11,000 platelets/mm²",
      "150,000-400,000 platelets/mm²",
      "150,000-200,000 platelets/mm²",
      "15,000-500,000 platelets/mm²"
    ],
    "answer": ["150,000-400,000 platelets/mm²"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 96,
    "question": "Normal clotting time range between",
    "options": [
      "3-10 mins",
      "5-10 mins",
      "1- 5 mins",
      "2- 5 mins",
      "10-15 mins"
    ],
    "answer": ["3-10 mins"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 97,
    "question": "Which of the following is not true of the Rhesus blood group?",
    "options": [
      "75%",
      "The rhesus blood group has naturally occurring antibody in the plasma to the antigen D",
      "any of the A,BO blood groups can be Rh – ve or Rh +ve",
      "Antibody D can only develop when a Rh-ve person is exposed to a Rh +ve blood",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "The rhesus blood group has naturally occurring antibody in the plasma to the antigen D"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 98,
    "question": "Bleeding time can be prolonged by",
    "options": [
      "lack of platelets",
      "lack of neutrophils",
      "lack of factor Xii",
      "lack of RBCs",
      "none of the above"
    ],
    "answer": ["lack of platelets"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 99,
    "question": "Which of these statements is not true of leucocytes",
    "options": [
      "they are nucleated",
      "they are confined to blood",
      "they have amoeboid movement",
      "they are larger than RBCs",
      "they are chemotaxic"
    ],
    "answer": ["they are confined to blood"],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  },
  {
    "id": 100,
    "question": "The % range of body water that is total body water in females is",
    "options": ["45-60%", "54-70 %", "65-75%", "40-60%", "none of the above"],
    "answer": ["45-60%"],
    "explanation": "Female 50% \n Male 60% \n infant 75%",
    "topic": ""
  },
  {
    "id": 101,
    "question": "Regarding the lymphocytes",
    "options": [
      "the lymphocytes are the most abundant white cells of the blood",
      "lymphocytes only leave the blood at sites of inflammation",
      "all B lymphocytes become plasma cells after they have been stimulated",
      "all T lymphocytes become plasma cells after they have been stimulated"
    ],
    "answer": [
      "all B lymphocytes become plasma cells after they have been stimulated"
    ],
    "explanation": "",
    "topic": "Blood and Body fluid"
  }
]
